Finding Aid for Brecken Family papers, 1894-1937, 1965
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Brecken Family papers 1894-1937, 1965 1913-1918
Brecken Family.
1 linear foot
91436 Aa 2
Grand Rapids, Michigan, family. Brief family history; letters to Clarence Brecken, also his journal, while stationed at Fort Benjamin Harrison during World War I; journal of Jennie Brecken, 1965; legal documents; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by the daughter of Clarence and Jennie Brecken, Vivian J. Ellis (Donor No. 7877 ) in October 1990.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Clarence E. Brecken (1893-1983) and Jennie A. Bentley (1892-1988) were married December 20, 1917, and moved to the Grand Rapids area in early 1918. Clarence was employed by the Michigan Central Railroad, and Jennie was a schoolteacher. In July 1918, during World War I, Clarence was drafted and sent for training to Fort Benjamin Harrison in Indiana. He returned to Grand Rapids in December 1918 at the end of the war. According to his final entry in his wartime journal, he intended to return to his position at Michigan Central Railroad. At some point before 1934, he became the store proprietor of Brecken's Ice Cream in Grand Rapids.
The general family history and names of family members of both the Brecken family and the Bentley family can be found in a summary written by Vivian Ellis, the daughter of Clarence and Jennie Brecken, in the "Family History" folder.
The majority of the correspondence in this Family papers series was received by Clarence Brecken from various members of his family during 1918 while in training at Fort Benjamin Harrison. The strengths of this correspondence are the descriptions of daily rural life during wartime and the concerns and fears of the families on the home-front. The letters include such topics as Jennie's first driving lessons, the evils of alcohol and tobacco use, hopes for the end of the war, Clarence's mother's fear of her other sons being drafted, and the spread of influenza. Also of interest are the Brown Family letters to Clarence which include discussions of the war as well as a letter from overseas.
The folders containing family photographs and World War I photographs comprise the bulk of the Photographs series; the photographs are generally identified. The World War I photographs include a number of photographs of Clarence and his brothers, Earl and Howard, in uniform and some of Clarence at his training camp. Most of the family photographs are group photographs taken outdoors and show aspects of rural life, such as the huge woodpiles for the mill in the background of many photographs in the "Bentley Family" folder. Of especial note is the interior photograph of Brecken's Ice Cream store in the "Grand Rapids Area" folder. The photograph was taken in 1934, and the various offerings and their prices can be seen in the background.
Subjects:
Brecken, Clarence E., 1893-1983.; Brecken, Jennie Bentley, 1892-1988.; Brecken family.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); Women--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; World War, 1914-1918.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Baldwin (Mich.); Bentley family.; Brecken family.; Camping.; Carriages and coaches.; Cedar Springs (Mich.); Dwellings--Michigan--McBain.; Farm houses.; Grand Rapids (Mich.); McBain (Mich.); Soda fountains--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Soldiers--American.; Tustin (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Family papers
  - Family History (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Brown Family, 1913-1918 (Box 1)
    - Family
      - 1913-1917 (Box 1)
      - July 27, 1918-September 11, 1918 (Box 1)
      - September 12, 1918-September 30, 1918 (Box 1)
      - October 1918 (Box 1)
      - November 1918 (Box 1)
    - Erma Bentley, December 1918-January 1919 (Box 1)
  - Legal Documents, 1894-1937 (Box 1)
  - Journals
    - Clarence Brecken, 1918 (Box 1)
    - Jennie Brecken, 1965 (Box 1)
- Family Photographs
  - World War I (Box 1)
  - Bentley Family (Box 1)
  - Brecken Family (Box 1)
  - Grand Rapids area (Box 1)
  - Cedar Springs (Box 1)
  - Vacations and Camping in Michigan (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)